Guide to the General Collection Manuscript Music Miscellany
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Soulage, Marcelle, 1894-1970
  - Music
    - Chamber music. Selections
      - [Chamber music], 1917-1934; 5 items. (Box Volume 61)
        Autograph manuscript music in an unidentified hand, with performance markings, signed by Soulage: Danse et berceuse, op. 9, no. 2, for violin and piano, score, with violin part for Berceuse, 1917 April-1918 January, with printer's markings by Evette & Schaeffer, plate number ES 1782; À Fauré, op. 22, no. 1, for unidentified trio and double bass, part for piano and double bass and part for first violin, with ownership stamp of Pierrette Bonniol-Bondy; and Offrande, op. 105, for violin and piano, score and part, 1930 June 7.
        Printed juvenile music for violin and piano (Paris: Éditions Paul Ricard, c1934), scores and parts: En première: pièces faciles; and Sans-Souci: marche burlesque, both with performance markings in unidentified hands and presentation inscriptions by Soulage to "professeur M. Bancroft-Bondy" and his students, 1934 July 17.
- Spalding, Albert, 1888-1953
  - Correspondence
    - Watkins, S. C. G., n.y. Apr 17; 1 item (1 p.); 18 cm. (Box Folder 363)
      Brief ALS, New York, in response to Watkin's request for an autograph.
      Former group number: 74 SPALDING, ALBERT
- Spontini, Gaspare, 1774-1851
  - Correspondence
    - Barbaia, Domenico, 1839 Dec 12; 1 item (2 p.); 24 cm. (Box Folder 364)
      ALS, Rome, to Barbaia, Naples, concerning church music in Rome and his affairs in Naples.
      Former group number: 75 SPONTINI, GASPARE
- Steffani, Agostino, 1654-1728
  - Music
    - Duets, voices, continuo
      - "Libro di duetti dello Stefani dell' Illmo. Sigre. Alfonso Marsili", [17--]; 1 v. of ms. music ([circa 280] p.); 22 x 29 cm. (Box Volume 41)
        Copyist's manuscript consisting of 22 chamber duets by Steffani.
        Binding: contemporary vellum.
        Purchased from Bernard Quaritch, Ltd., on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2003.
- Strauss, Johann, 1825-1899
  - Correspondence
    - Unidentified, n.y. Mar 1; 1 item (1 p.); 22 cm. (Box Folder 365)
      Brief ALS to "Monsieur le Directeur," requesting tickets for a performance.
      Former group number: 76 STRAUSS, JOHANN
      Gift of Harold Lamport, M.D., and Mrs. H. L. Friedman, 1961.
- Sturges, Marietta
  - Music
    - Unidentified
      Former group number: 77 STURGES, MARIETTA
      - Hymn book, [17--?]; 1 v. ([11] p. of ms. music); 23 cm. (Box Folder 366)
        Manuscript collection of hymn tunes, with meters and words, including a few American patriotic songs, signed by Marietta Sturges.
        The music is written in an unidentified hand, possibly by Sturges.
        Source unknown; found in Music Library stacks, 1935.
- Sullivan, Arthur, Sir, 1842-1900
  - Correspondence
    - Thornburgh, Mrs., 1895 Apr 30; 1 item (1 p.); 17 cm. (Box Folder 367)
      Brief ALS, arranging a meeting, with envelope labelled "W. S. G.".
      Former group number: 78 SULLIVAN, ARTHUR
      Gift, 1942.
    - Unidentified, n.y. May 16; 1 item (1 p.); 18 cm. (Box Folder 368)
      Brief ALS to "Minnie," mentioning his trip to Egypt.
- Thomas, Ambroise, 1811-1896
  - Music
    - Songe d'une nuit d'été
      Opera, with libretto by Joseph-Bernard Rosier and Adolphe de Leuven.
      First performed 1850; revised version performed 1886.
      - Revisions for Songe d'une nuit d'été, [circa 1886]; [49] p. of ms. music; 35 cm. (Box Oversize Folder 87)
        Holograph sketches and drafts in short score and full score, for revision of the 1850 version.
        Includes additional blank pages.
- Treadwell, James W.
  - Music
    - Child's hymn
      - "A child's hymn: composed and dedicated to Persis C. Eldredge on the occasion of her birthday, November 2d, 1876 / by J. W. Treadwell", 1 ms. score ([5] p.); 23 cm. (Box Folder 396)
        Hymn for voice and piano, score, autograph manuscript, with performance instructions. Laid in is a manuscript note to Persis C. Eldredge, signed "Elizabeth E. Eldredge," about the hymn.
        Purchased from Robert H. Rubin Books on the Jockey Hollow Fund, 2009.
- Verdi, Giuseppe, 1813-1901
  - Correspondence
    - De Amicis, Giuseppe, 1889 June 24; 1 item (2 p.). (Box Folder 428)
      Autograph letter, signed, with envelope, discussing financial matters.
      Accompanied by a carte-de-visite photograph of Verdi, by Charles Reutlinger, Paris, undated.
      Purchased from Moirandat (J. A. Stargardt sale, 2001 November 13-14, lot 1009) on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2001.
    - Guidi, Francesco, 1839 Sep 9; 1 item (2 p.); 21 cm. (Box Folder 369)
      ALS, Bussetto, to Guidi, Milan, declining to set librettos sent by Guidi.
      Former group number: 79 VERDI, GIUSEPPE
      Purchased by Lisa Cox on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund.
    - Jacovacci, Vincenzo, 1858 March 29; 1 item (2 p.). (Box Folder 427)
      Autograph letter, signed, Naples, to the manager of the Teatro Apollo, Rome, concerning censorship of Un ballo en maschera. Verdi discusses censorship of the opera in Naples and asks whether another play, also based on the assassination of Gustavus III of Sweden, has been censored in Rome.
      Accompanied by an English translation made by a former owner.
      Purchased from Maggs Brothers on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2009.
    - Unidentified, 1891 October 31; 1 item (2 p.). (Box Folder 426)
      Autograph letter, signed, Busseto, to "Caro Generale," recommending a soldier, a son of Giacomo Persico, in the 43rd Regiment of Viacenza. The letter also discusses flooding of the Po River and effects on Verdi's farm and neighbors.
  - Music
    - Giorno di regno. Sinfonia
      Overture for opera, alternative title Il finto Stanislao, with libretto by Felice Romani, after Alexandre Duval's Le faux Stanislas.
      First performed 1840.
      - "Sinfonia nell'opera Il finto Stanislao / di G. Verdi", [circa 1840]; 1 ms. score ([20] p.); 23 x 31 cm. (Box Folder 393)
        Score, contemporary copyist's manuscript.
    - Luisa Miller. German Italian
      Opera, with libretto by Salvadore Cammarano, based on Friedrich von Schiller's play Kabale und Liebe.
      First performed 1849.
      - "Luisa Miller: melodramma tragico in tre atti / sinfonia musica del Sigr. Mo. Giuseppe Verdi", [ca. 1850]; 1 ms. score (2 v.); 34 cm. (Box Volume 29-30)
        Score in two volumes, written in manuscript in the hands of several copyists, with text in Italian and German translation. Annotations on the title page of each act list performances in Italian cities, including Alba, 1882; Alessandria, 1851; Bari, 1877-1878; Bergamo, 1851 and 1885-1886; Brescia, 1887; Verdi's Busseto estate, 1890; Casale Monferrato, 1878; Fabriano, n.d.; Faenza, n.d.; Fano, 1877-1878; Fiume, n.d.; Genoa, 1850 and 1889; Gorizia, 1889; Mantua, 1878 and 1887; Milan, 1881; Padua, 1879-1880; Parma, n.d.; Pistoia, 1890; Reggio, 1851 and 1883; Riva, 1878; Rome, 1885 and n.d.; Rovigo, 1850; San Remo, 1880-1881; Turin, n.d.; Vercelli, 1851-1852; Vicenza, 1888; and Zara, 1852 and n.d.
        Stamps on title pages and throughout each act indicate that the score was rented through the Leipzig office of Verdi's publisher Ricordi, apparently during a German revival of the opera in the 1920s. Blank pages following each act are stamped 1929. Part of act two and missing fragments of a few other pages have been replaced by later copyists. Metronome markings, cuts, and other performance markings appear throughout the score. The title page of act one is signed by conductor Leopoldo Mugnone.
        Bound by a former owner. "D. Walter" stamped on each spine.
- Viardot-Garcia, Pauline, 1821-1910
  - Correspondence
    - Bardeleben, Mademoiselle, [1882, 1883]; 2 items. (Box Folder 370)
      Two ALS, with two envelopes, to Bardeleben, Paris, one regarding lessons, and one regarding concerts.
      In French. Accompanied by a typscript English translation.
      Former group number: 80 VIARDOT-GARCIA, PAULINE
      Purchased from Henry Bristow on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund.
    - Moscheles, Charlotte, 1862 Oct 5; 1 item (3 p.); 21 cm. (Box Folder 371)
      ALS, Baden-Baden, Montebello, regarding Viardot-Garcia's student and friend, Julienne Orwil.
      Purchaseed from Henry Bristow on the Edith French Anderson memorial Fund, 1997.
    - Unidentified, [18]85, n.d.; 2 items. (Box Folder 372)
      Two ALS, one acknowledging a letter just received, and one refusing an invitation.
- Wagner, Cosima, 1837-1930
  - Correspondence
    - Lewes, George Henry, n.d.; 1 item (3 p.); 18 cm. (Box Folder 373)
      ALS, [London?], about a meeting.
      Former group number: 81 WAGNER, COSIMA
      Gift, 1948.
- Walton, William, 1902-1983
  - Correspondence
    - Newman, Ernest, 1929-1959, n.d.; 8 items. (Box Folder 374)
      Seven ALS, with six envelopes, discussing Façade; the Viola Concerto and Symphony no. 1, and performances of both by Sir Hamilton Harty; Christopher Hassall's libretto for Troilus and Cressida; and a sonata for violin and piano. One ALS, with envelope, to his widow Vera Newman, offering condolence on Newman's death.
      Former group number: 82 WALTON, WILLIAM
  - Music
    - Henry V
      Music for the film directed by Laurence Olivier. Composed 1943-1944.
      - Excerpts from Henry V, [circa 1943-1944]; [18] p. of ms. music; 48 cm. (Box Volume 57)
        Music for the Battle of Agincourt, holograph score, with some revisions, annotated by Walton "147A," "No. 147B," and "No. 147C." Possibly used by Muir Mathieson in conducting for the film and for his Suite from Henry V (Oxford University Press, 1964).
        Annotation in an unidentified hand: "Suite / No. 3 / Charge & Battle."
        Purchased by Alan Thomas (Oxfam charity auction, Christie's, 1964 November 17, lot 138). Purchased by Halsted B. VanderPoel, 1966 February 19.
        Purchased from Bernard Quaritch, Ltd. (Christie's Halsted B. VanderPoel sale, 2004 March 3, lot 356), on the Library Associates Endowment Fund, 2004.
      - Henry V screenplay, [circa 1944]; 1 item (91 l.); 33 cm. (Box Folder 394)
        Screenplay, typescript mimeograph, with cues from the film, apparently for use in making dubbed versions.
        Purchased from Cinema Bookshop on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2002.
    - Sinfonia concertante, piano, orchestra
      Composed while Walton was living in London with the Sitwell family; published 1928; revised 1943.
      Walton dedicated the three movements of the work to Edith, Osbert, and Sacheverell Sitwell.
      - "Sinfonia concertante: for orchestra with pianoforte (quasi obbligato) / by William Walton", [ca. 1927]; 1 ms. score (3 v.); 45 cm. (Box Volume 31)
        Score, with corrections and conductor's markings. The score varies from the first published edition and is apparently an earlier version of the work. Accompanied by a fragment of score paper with Walton's name and the Sitwells' London address, written by Walton in holograph.
        Purchased at Sotheby's, London (1999 Dec 9, lot 265), on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund.
- Wolf-Ferrari, Ermanno, 1876-1948
  - Correspondence
    - Baumann, Otto, 1915-1918; 9 items. (Box Folder 375)
      Nine ALS concerning their friendship, Wolf-Ferrari's life in Munich and Zurich during the First World War, and his views on music and art.
      Former group number: 83 WOLF-FERRARI, ERMANNO
  - Music
    - Chiese di Venezia
      Composed circa 1948, incomplete.
      - Fragments and drafts for Chiese di Venezia, 1947-[circa 1948]; [circa 120] p. of ms. music; 35 cm. and smaller. (Box Volume 60)
        Section titled "S. Maria Gloriosa dei Frari," score, autograph manuscript, and drafts for this and other sections, short score, autograph manuscript, some dated 1947 August-September.
        Purchased from Lisa Cox (Sotheby's sale, 2005 May 20, lot 185) on the Edith and Richard French Fund, 2005.
    - Quartets, strings, A minor
      - "Quartetto in la minore per 2 violini, viola, e violoncello / di Ermanno Wolf-Ferrari, Monaco, Gennaio 1895", 1895 January; 1 ms. score ([44] p.); 23 x 32 cm. (Box Volume 59)
        Score, holograph. Dated at Monaco (i.e. Munich).
        Dedication on title page to "Prof. Ludwig Abel."
        Purchased from Lisa Cox (Sotheby's sale, 2005 May 20, lot 184) on the Edith and Richard French Fund, 2005.
    - Quartets, strings, C major
      - "Quartetto in C-dur per due violini, viola, e vcello / di Ermanno Wolf, Luglio-Agosto 1893", 1893 July-August; 1 ms. score ([63] p.); 25 x 33 cm. (Box Volume 58)
        Score, holograph, with a few revisions.
        Dedication on title page to "Theodore und Hermann Kilian."
        Purchased from Lisa Cox (Sotheby's sale, 2005 May 20, lot 186) on the Edith and Richard French Fund, 2005.
    - Unidentified
      - "Serenata", undated; 1 ms. score ([3] p.); 35 cm. (Box Oversize Folder 88)
        Incomplete score, holograph, for an unidentified work for orchestra.
        Purchased from Eberhard Koestler on the Library Associates Endowment Fund, 2002.
- Wolff, Albert, 1835-1891
  - Other Papers
    - Essay about the Mueller Quartet, [18--]; 1 item (5 leaves); 22 cm. (Box Folder 376)
      Essay, holograph, with brief corrections, about the Mueller quartet and German music.
      The essay is titled "Chronique."
      Former group number: 84 WOLFF, ALBERT
      Purchase, 1931.
- Unidentified
  - Music
    - Unidentified
      Former group number: 85 UNIDENTIFIED
      - "Le mystère de Noël", 1899 Sep 16; 1 ms. score (104 p.); 32 cm. (Box Volume 32)
        Cantata for solo children's voices, children's chorus, and organ, written in manuscript, with corrections, in an unidentified hand. The composer is unidentified, but the work possibly originates from Lyon, France. The text concerns the nativity of Christ.
      - "Musica", 1929; 1 v. (8 p.); 23 cm. (Box Folder 377)
        Manuscript poem with ink and crayon drawings and two printed pages of music.
        Inscribed on last leaf: "For Bacchus and Sylvia that Cupid's fire may brighter burn, Spring 1929."
        Laid in: menu for "Bimillennium Horatianum Cena."
        In French and English.
        Contains stamp of Richard Montgomery Gilchrist Potter.
        Source unknown
      - Orthodox Eastern Church music, [17--?]; 1 v. ([324] p.); 19 cm. (Box Volume 33)
        Bound autograph manuscript in an unidentified hand of the Psalms of David and other church music in Ancient Greek, set to music for use in the churches at Constantinople.
        Gift of the Brothers in Unity, 1871.
      - Poem and music, 1892-93; 1 item (2 p.); 23 x 31 cm. (Box Oversize Folder 33)
        Sheet containing a poem, with first line, "Non questo: serbi l'album del tuo cuore," autograph manuscript, signed Giosue de [Bisi?], Viggiano, [18]93 Oct 5; on verso are two lines of music with words, autograph manuscript, signed L. C. M. [Bolorfone?], 1892 Feb 15.
        Gift, 1989.
      - "Raccolta di canzoni ed arie nazionali napolitane e balli popolari per pianoforte", [17--?]; ca. 100 p. of ms. music; 18 x 24 cm. (Box Volume 34)
        Volume of untitled pieces for piano, written in manuscript by an unidentified composer or copyist, most with song texts included.
        Purchased from Michel Bouvier on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund.
      - "Soirs d'amour / de Régnier", 1895 October-November; 1 ms. score ([25] p.); 35 cm. (Box Volume 62)
        Song cycle by an unidentified composer, on texts possibly by Henri de Régnier, dedicated to Sybil Sanderson.
        Score, manuscript in an unidentified hand, with printer's markings by Huegel, copyright 1896. Song titles are: Le beinvenue d'amour; Prés de l'eau; Si j'ai parlé; Les fontaines; Au bois des frênes, unidentified signature, dated 1895 October 2; and Echo d'amour, unidentified signature, dated 1895 November 18.
        Plate numbers in manuscript: H et Cie 8376-8381.
      - Treatise on singing, [1700s?]; 1 v. ([circa 80] p., mostly music); 35 cm. (Box Volume 63)
        Treatise, manuscript in an unidentified hand, on singing technique, consisting mostly of exercises for voice and piano.
        Purchased from Librarie Musicale Ancienne on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2002.
  - Other Papers
    - "Proportio harmonica tonorum, or, The true distance of musical notes: as the same is mathematically proved and brought to ocular demonstration", [circa 1750]; 1 v. ([circa 200] p.); 21 cm. (Box Volume 35)
      Manuscript treatise in an unidentified hand on equal temperament, written "for the sake of a young family." The author discusses theories of musical temperament, gives rules for tuning a harpsichord, and addresses time signatures, note values, and intervals.
      Purchased from Bernard Quaritch, Ltd., on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2009.
    - Treatise on harmony, [circa 1860]; 1 v. ([circa 600] p.); 29 cm. (Box Volume 64)
      Manuscript treatise on harmony, with music examples, written in an unidentified hand.
      Caption title: Seconde partie.
      Binding: contemporary paper, including fragments of advertisements for an unidentified French bookseller, circa 1853.
      Formerly owned by Georges Lauweryns.